# Alan Guedes — C.V. ☑ a.guedes@ucl.ac.uk • ③ alanlivio.github.io • in alanlivio • ③ alanlivio • ③ alanlivio

## **Shorbio**

I am a Computer Scientist (Ph.D. & Postdoc) interested in Machine Learning (ML) methods for the next generation of immersive systems and graph-based data. My career can be seen threefold. In research, I worked on research Multimedia & ML projects, contributed to communities (Springer, ACM SIGMM and SBC WebMedia](http://webmedia.org.br)), and have been awarded research funding. In teaching, I co-supervised students, acted as a lecturer on under- and post-graduate courses, and organized workshops to promote student interest in public engagement. Last, I added value to the industry through open source and standards in TV forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum).

# **Experiences**

Work

### UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream project funded by EPSRC to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

#### PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR project, funded by Microsoft & RNP to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML (Anti-Money Laundry) project, funded by BTG Bank, to detect financial transactions risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP project, funded by RNP, to develop a blockchain-based system for academic certificates.

#### Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer
Highlights: multiple awarded social impact projects.

2012-2013

- Brasil4D project, funded by World Bank, to transmit interactive TV content with social features to low-income families. Its results were published in a public report

Education

# PUC-Rio

Ph.D. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis concepts used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses, to develop a reference implementation for TV manufacturers;
- SBTVD Conformance Test Suite project, funded by Brazilian Ministry of Science and Technology, to be used by TV manufacturers

## UFPB

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis concepts used in the awarded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- GingaStore, funded by RNP, to design a broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

#### HEPR

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware

2005-2009

- Ginga CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

# Research

### Publications....

Google Scholar shows 40+ published papers, 100+ citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some selected publications.

Elsevier Book Chapter		2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.		2022
•	2016, 2	-
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).		2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021, 2021, 2020, 2021, 2020, 2020, 2021, 2020,		
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.		2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.	2	2019
Committees		
ACM, Special Interest Group on Multimedia		
	2020-to	oday
BR Computing Society (SBC), Web&Mulimedia Committee		
Steering Committee	2021-to	oday
	2017-to	-
- WebMedia conference reviewer (2017-today), chair of Undergrad workshop (2018), chair of Demos (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	s Works	shop
Springer Reviewer	2022 +	
- Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023)	2022-to	oaay
- Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022)		
Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD)		
Academic member at Technical Module contributing to TV middleware standards	2017-2	2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Academic member at $SG-16/Q13$ contributing to IPTV middleware standards	2017-2	2021
Teaching		
UCL		
	2022-to	
SBC WebMedia	2010	oday
Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.	2018-2	
PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to nectored students (20 L)	,	2022
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)		2022 2019
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students $(30+)$ Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students $(30+)$ .		2022
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)	2	2022 2019
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students $(30+)$ Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students $(30+)$ . Japan International Cooperation Agency	2	2022 2019 2013
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR	2	2022 2019 2013 2012
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR  Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)	2	2022 2019 2013 2012
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR  Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)  UFPB  Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (1stering & Awards	2	2022 2019 2013 2012 2012
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR  Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)  UFPB  Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (1st	2 2 5+) 2	2022 2019 2013 2012 2012
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR  Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)  UFPB  Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (1sterior of the countries professionals (30+)  Funding & Awards  Microsoft&RNP  Approved as PI in VideoMR project  ACM	2 2 5+) 2	2019 2013 2012 2011 2011 2010
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR  Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)  UFPB  Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (1stering & Awards  Microsoft&RNP  Approved as PI in VideoMR project  ACM  SIGMM Travel Award for MMSys	2 2 5+) 2 2	2022 2019 2013 2012 2011 2010 2019
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)  Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30+).  Japan International Cooperation Agency  Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (30+)  RNP ESR  Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)  UFPB  Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (1sterior of the countries professionals (30+)  Funding & Awards  Microsoft&RNP  Approved as PI in VideoMR project  ACM	2 2 2 5+) 2 2	2019 2013 2012 2011 2010

Multiple TV associations	
FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project	2014
SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project	2013
PremioTV on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project	2013
ITU	
IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore project	2012
Skills	
Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writing.	
Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills.	
<b>Programing</b> : Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Docker.	
Social: Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, teamwork, lead-by-exa	mple attitudes.
Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).	
Training	
UCL	
Data Protection for Researchers; Fundamentals in Research Funding.	2022-2023
Nature	
Interpreting Scientific Results; Focus on Peer Review.	2022-2023

# References

ITU

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.

ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups

- Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. Ph.D. supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- $\ Roberto \ Azevedo, \ roberto. azevedo @disneyresearch.com. \ Tele Midia \ collaborator.$

2023